hi
welcome back to the alarm room love in
the time of the virus
or we could call it sending the virus to
the middle of the sun
i'm not sure which one i like better
and you saw one of my favorite images in
the world
which is a croissant in paris
you know wandering around paris and i
like to stop by every bullet journey
i see and there's one every three or
four
doors so it's kind of difficult for me
to walk through paris
and i don't know i got the recipe
for that croissant and i tried to make
it at home and it's almost a whole
pound half a kilo of butter and
so anyway i decided i shouldn't eat so
many uh anyway they are delicious
why we're talking about that we're gonna
i also don't remember let's see we're
gonna talk about it
okay uh he starts with a question
papankarimpuche starts with a question
so you know if someone comes up and says
to us do you remember that word from
last episode we said
something in the in the palm of your
hand and and this is your main practice
this is like
the number one practice you're working
on it's the one that's at hand
all the time and if somebody comes up to
you and says hey man what do you what
are you focusing on nowadays you know
what's your
number one buddhist practice and i don't
know about you
but if you're like me you know i got
practices and practices and practices
and practices and
i'll never forget i had a student from
burma
many years ago maybe 25 30 years ago and
he learned one more meditation from me i
was having a class
and he said well i don't know if i'm
going to show up you know and i said
well why
and he says i don't need one more thing
to feel guilty about
that i'm not doing you that you taught
me you know and
and he says i'm going a little bit crazy
uh feeling guilty about
trying to do all the things you taught
me you know and so
means means
you know what are you gonna focus on so
i think it's important for all of us
uh to find one thing that you're going
to be focusing on
and obviously in this in this
lamrim uh retreat that we're doing right
now
we're trying to focus on the idea of
of this experience and
and i i don't think we've really gotten
yet
the instructions for triggering that
experience
but still i think hearing about it
over and over again is planting seeds in
our mind to have that experience
and if we have that experience then i
believe
if enough of us have this experience
together then i think the virus couldn't
uh survive around us you know so i think
that
that's my idea how to work on the virus
and then you know i was
having breakfast and i was thinking come
on you know get real
uh you know you have to study the the
news this morning
you have to see what the economist says
about the progress with the virus uh
vaccination
you know you have to think about is
american airlines
idea about flying planes safe and i
caught myself
thinking like that and and uh
and then they had an article about in
some country uh
people heard people were going started
they heard that drinking methyl alcohol
which is poison
uh was good to prevent the virus and 400
people died
uh drinking uh you know hard alcohol
uh that you use for cleaning and then i
i remember i was thinking oh those
people are
crazy you know they're living in such a
strange
society where they would drink methyl
alcohol
and die because they drink a poison
because they thought it would help with
the virus somehow and then i caught
myself
and i thought well the vaccination is
the same you know it's
it's actually based on a wrong idea you
see what i mean uh
it's it's the same thing if it works if
they make one that works
uh it's not because of something in the
chemicals
okay it's because of it's because of
some kind of attitude
that you and i have if we can have this
body cheddar
experience you know if we can
make contact with i don't know
a few billion being directly and if we
can
comfort them and say don't worry i'll
take care of you one by one
then then that's the real antidote for
the virus and the
in the vaccination and the methyl
alcohol i think they're just about the
same
if if it works it's because of your love
it's not because of what's in the
in the vaccination okay and and i look
forward to the vaccination and i think i
think it'll work
but i i think we have to have a lot of
love
for it to work we have to think about
other people at this time
anyway if someone asks you so so what's
your main practice gishla
because you know i by the way i have
people come up to me and say
uh you know you've taught us like a
hundred different meditations and
well which which one do you want us to
focus on you know which should we hold
in our
as our main practice you know and then
he says
somebody asked you this question
oh my main practice is tantra high
agriva
which means horse throat tantra it's a
special tantrum chakr
which means vajrapani the the buddha
with the
vajra in his hand and then jig which is
bhairova
which means the frightener or the lord
of terror
and john dun these are difficult dun dun
gin
is a difficult word dra means oh
something like those three
or you could say vajrayogini or you
could say tara or you could say medicine
buddha
you know i'm focusing on that
means i'm reciting that sadhana you know
that's my regular son dun means to
recite every morning what's the sansgrid
and it's a famous mistranslation that
people do of the yoga sutra
it means to do your daily memorization
and recitation
and all the translations say self-study
or something like that it has nothing to
do that
anyway means
it means to to recite your sadness every
morning from memory begin
is the present participle i'm doing that
every day
okay that's what i'm doing every day yes
sir
same moments you know we say stuff like
that but
uh most of us if you figure out what's
our
as to uh
for
yeah fifty dollars you gotta remind me
okay i'll forget
yeah most of us are most of us
what's our main practice it's uh
thinking that things come this way
and then getting irritated with things
or else wanting things
uh the wrong way okay and that's that's
our main
that's our core practice you want a core
practice that's our core practice
okay those three animals in the middle
of the real life right there in the
corridor wheel of life
okay
means you see a lot of people like that
you know that's what there's
okay and i got a picture here of um just
a palm and a hand
so you could remember this expression
you know what's our
main practice what's the thing we're
focusing on and it's you know
this thing in the palm of the hand where
this is your main practice this is the
one you carry around with you all the
time okay and i i like this picture i
don't know why
i think it's kind of artistic i guess
all right
and he says wow he was a master of
everything you know he had mastered
countless
scriptures his commentaries are
unbelievable i in fact i was trying to
read one yesterday and i was like
i actually decided not to teach it to
you guys in october because it's just
too difficult
and so
he was a master of everything of all
this uh
by the way we are going to do his
sadhana but we're not going to do
a commentary on emptiness which is often
printed with the sunnah
i thought it would be nice to do them
together but it's too it's too far out
it would take a year to teach it
day two too matsimba means but he wasn't
satisfied
with learning all these topics and uh
simba seminivo j d
uh okay sam rimboche is a beautiful
expression which means
this jewel mind this jewel state of mind
meaning you know this experience uh
having this experience with other people
sem rinpoche this jewel state of mind
chill
for the sake of getting it
through he took off across the ocean
to get the instructions on bodhichitta
so there was a famous
llama living in suvarna de vipa
the golden isle which is
indonesia part of indonesia what's that
called
sumatra okay and anyway he went off
he said i'm gonna i heard there's a
great teacher
of bodhichitta living in the isles
around uh java and sumatra so he took
off
on a bone you know uh 1 000 years ago
you know this guy this guy this llama
you know
took off from north india and went all
the way to the ocean
and then went 13 months
extremely difficult journey extremely
dangerous journey
we have in this next this next image
i kind of feel like this image says it
all
uh he's he's in this tiny boat
on a very dangerous sea and and it was
extremely
dangerous uh to sail in those days and i
don't think this this painting is an
exaggeration
why is red important
he always wore a red hat uh socappa wore
a gold one
so if you see a tanka and they have a
red panda tat
that's that's artisan and if it's gold
well that's
some kind of so i picked the red shim
and this is not an exaggeration i mean
this is probably what it felt like
uh to travel those 13 months
to travel across the ocean
to meet this llama and he was so strict
with his vows
that he refused to take his monks robes
off he did the whole trip in his monk's
rooms
and when he got there what happened that
was famous when he got there
yeah yeah i don't i don't think it was
that much but he
yeah he refused to go to uh
by the way that teacher's name was also
dharma kirti but it's a different derma
kitty
and sometimes he's called suvarnadvipa
guru
the the lama from the golden isle of
sumatra
but he refused to go directly to his
classes he checked him out first
you know he probably got to indonesia
and got an internet connection and
checked out this person to see if there
were any
scandals or any problems with this
person okay
and he did not go directly to the
teacher he studied the teacher first
after the thirteen months on the ocean
okay uh
la master ningba la deen damn young
studied the complete instructions
for having this experience
of bodhichitta directly from lama llamas
and he made uh bodhichitta
his palm practice you know the
at the center of his palm practice
and he had many many teachers in his
life atisha but he respected
uh this teacher above all and he
he was uh more devoted
to this teacher than any other of his
many teachers
the one who gave him the instructions on
bodhichi
shen tawani sterling basem
this is a very interesting sentence
shen means you know if you looked at
this teacher sudhwan avipa guru from
another point of view
shen tawa histawa
his philosophical school was
symptom he was a mind only practitioner
okay therefore he was mawa
he was lower lower school okay and it's
it's very interesting that pablo graham
j would throw that in
you know from the point of view of his
emptiness
understanding he was actually lower than
ati shah and songkhapa and people like
that
his his viewpoint was middleweight sorry
mind only so why should
atisha whose viewpoint is much higher
i respect this this teacher above all
his teachers
it's because he taught him this form of
love
universal love okay that's very
beautiful
okay
us guys we should work on on this
this is the practice we should work on a
tube means
i think i can do it you know i think i
could it took
i think two means to be able to right
and it means
yeah i think i could do it you know
after hearing this alarm rim
due to the hard work of tim and jing-mei
and seiji and a hundred other people
you know you should be saying by now in
this course you say i took
hey i think i could pull that off i
think i could do that you know i'm gonna
i'm gonna go for it okay
a2 that good thing that's how you have
to think okay you have to think like
that
means body and mind headquarters
okay body and mind headquarters
for sem qiawa what's that mean
you ain't never gonna find a body and a
mind
meaning you ain't never gonna find a
situation
better than today that and actually the
virus is even better than normal
okay you're not gonna find a better
world you're not gonna find a better
human body
you're not gonna find a better iq you're
not going to find a better dharma iq
than the one you got right now he says
he says that
you you will never be able to find a
better chance
than the one you have right now you have
an extraordinary chance
to get to this state of mind to have
this experience you are
perfectly situated in the balance of
suffering and happiness
in this coveted world to have the
experience of bodhichitta if you just
try if you just put it here
and and focus on it for a while then you
you couldn't have a better chance and
this is perfect everything's perfect
right now
they say in the god realms people
can't develop bodhichitta very easily
because there's not enough
problems but we got this virus problem i
mean so everything's perfect we have
we have enough food there'll be some
economic problems but we have enough
food
you know everyone's got a place to stay
and
you can see the real situation of the
world is
the world is showing its true nature
nowadays
it's always been like this there's been
a pandemic going on since human beings
started
it's called death but it's just more
obvious nowadays
so it's a good time to practice love
it's a good time to
to try to to try to reach this kind of
love
this sentence is extremely important for
seiji
okay so we have the body in mind we have
the perfect circumstances
and we should be doing sem zhang
yeah what's the other name for that
lo john okay so you know don't let
people
don't let people tell you mental
development or something like that
some incredibly bad translation
extraordinarily poor
translation okay uh here it is
here's the real meaning of lojong and
he's playing with us
he doesn't call it lojo he calls it by
its full name
chang ki senchong
practicing bodhichitta trying to get the
bodhichitta that's what lo
means and i told you guys a million
times in
aci 14 well here it is okay
means chicla if you get one
good teaching on
trying to to develop this bodhichitta
experience
if you were looking for a body and mind
that was ideal situation and an ideal
world to get bodhichitta you're there
already and
you're in the middle of the best
teaching
for developing bodhichitta okay you're
in the middle of a
of a extensive lamrim this llama is
going to go on for 14 years or something
you know inshallah so uh
we you know you can't you how can you do
better than that you're sitting in the
middle of the greatest long room
ever written and you're sitting in a
world
which is comfortable but dangerous and
that's perfect
okay uh sam junkie dumbass
you not give him a dinner together there
is no better
dharma you could be working on to get
bodhichitte
if you get to this alarm room
being taught on the internet
in this world which has enough food
uh for us we and enough housing
and a a virus that could kill you
this is perfect you know this is like
and if you can't get bodhichitta now
with this teaching and with this world
that we're
experiencing right now then you're like
a
person who goes to
[Music]
paris and doesn't go to the bulartry
and doesn't get a parisian croissant
okay i'll give you guys a quiz
how come i there were days
in paris when i couldn't get my
[Music]
croissant
well no when you go you always got jet
lag to come from the united states you
always
that's a terrible jet lag that's one of
the worst is to go to europe from the us
and then what happens
no you wake up late and the best
bellagio is they don't serve consonants
after like 11 or 12. you go there and
they're like stupid american we don't
have croissants after 11 o'clock
why not because we don't make them out
of uh horse oil
like you do they and they get bad after
them
we want them fresh anyway it's a thing
so
shin dupong okay say shinto pang
shindu pan okay pan
uh pung means
fat in chinese language shin depak
probably means very fat
this is a covered tummy uh no
but in tibetan shinto pong means uh
how do you say how would you say it you
go to paris and you don't get a
croissant
it's a great loss shinto pung means
incredible loss
okay shinto pong means you got the best
teaching
you got the best long room you're in the
middle of those instructions you know
you got enough to eat you have a place
to stay
you're stuck at home a lot
and and you see the real nature of this
life which is dangerous
and then if you don't pick up your
croissant then then
you know you're crazy you're not going
to get a better chance than that okay
you blew it okay
all right chug pens into me and say
not
uh you see people comparing dharma
practices
and uh they think me say child
[Music]
is a special yoga practice where
uh you go out and you collect the
pollen from certain flowers
and then you you make a pill out of it
tiny pills and if you've reached a
certain kind of
meditation level that's enough to live
on okay
and so i i know some foreigners some
americans
and there's some europeans and they they
tried to do chilean
and they they went and you know i it's
kind of nice that
uh westerners try this stuff
because tibetans know better but uh
there's some westerners reading
something like this and they run out and
they get some flour and pollen and they
make little pills
and then i saw these guys they did
chilean for a month they lived off these
pills for a month and they were they
looked like from a concentration camp
you know
they looked terrible and uh it looked
like they're about to die
and that's not human okay chilean means
if you have this stage of meditation and
you take this tiny pill
you look like seiji you look all
you know muscular and strong and happy
and healthy
okay so that's not chilling okay if you
get skinny
you're not doing tuna if you look great
you're doing chilling okay
young young cher means the the pinnacle
okay
yangtze means it means the it means the
top of the top
yang means also right so say means tip
so they think oh this is the pinnacle of
of religious practice if i could live
off those little pills
then i'd be a real saint this is what it
would be to be a real saint
lom is a special verb that means to have
delusions
big delusions you know like those guys
who say i'm napoleon or something
in the in the crazy house that's called
loam
so here he says those those people who
think
uh they they're gonna eat these little
pills and
and then they don't get skinny then
they're they must be real meditators and
he says love that's all alone delusion
and then you ask them well what do
what's your opinion about butter cheddar
and they say well then you know
that's a nice thing that's okay but i'm
working on children you know
the bodhichitta is you know it's one of
those things
people talk about it's not a big deal
okay here it says
kel chung it means not a big deal okay
so we see people wandering
in the opposite direction from
enlightenment
okay like there's enlightenment you know
10 miles that way and they're like
wandering out of the desert somewhere
completely confused you know i'm doing
too late
wait wait you got to get there no no no
i'm going to go over there you know so
that's called the
gula to make a mistake on your path okay
is an expression in buddhism it means
this is something we see every day you
know don't think i'm describing some
crazy situation
means seeing entity and but what it
means in
in colloquial tibetan is come on you can
see these
people everywhere you know every dharma
group in this world
you can see people who consider
some little uh yoga practice to be more
important than loving other people okay
all right um
now let's get back to us guys who are
you know
we're not crazy we're trying to get uh
bodhichitta and he says look if you
could have the real
experience uh just once
okay they might not so jakey
if you can't get to that real experience
at least try keep trying keep
knocking away on it you know like try
one day
and then try the next day and then try
the next day so what he says here is
look
if you don't have this direct experience
with all the
people of the universe in 20 minutes
then keep knocking away on it so chain
means
keep keep getting used to it know what
timber
means keep getting used to the idea
listen
about it learn about it talk about it
with your friends
keep getting used to the idea that it is
possible to meet every living being in
the universe
within 20 minutes and
and make a commitment to them to take
care of them as if you were their mother
or their father okay
so get just to get used to the idea so
what he's saying here is
look if you don't have this experience
tomorrow don't freak out
okay just keep working on it keep trying
and and get used to the idea keep
thinking about it and then it's going to
help it
grow in your mind
here's another item then uh
if you don't have time or you're too
busy to
to think about it constantly then please
think about it once in a while
okay okay uh
at least get in the general mood
try to get in the general mood of it you
know like
on your way to work uh in your car
or or while you're having dinner while
you're watching netflix
just think about it once a while and say
you know
that'd be cool if i could do that that
that'd be kind of cool
so even if you don't practice it every
day consciously
or purposely but at least try to
entertain the idea once in a while
that's called
get used to the idea get accustomed to
the idea okay
that's what you should do but the key is
negative at the end of a sentence okay
ki
but if you don't think
it's worth your meditation time if your
meditation time is too booked up
uh with meditating on vajrayogini or
tara or
medicine buddha and you don't have time
because your meditation time is all
booked up with these high
tantric deities then then
somebody if if that's your practice okay
if you think that focusing on vagina
guinea
tara or medicine buddha is the main
thing
and you put all your effort into that
and you don't have
time during your daily practice
to think about this experience
it is a useless effort okay meaningless
exertion okay it's a meaningless
work that you're doing with tantra if
you're not working on this state of mind
everything else becomes you know
meaningless
exhausting yourself no one means to
exhaust yourself without any point okay
de hajjan pambayinsum and there would be
no greater loss in your life
okay to spend your life that way
there that'd be like going to paris a
thousand times
and not getting a croissant okay so
that completes this section of the text
we're going to be going on during the
next retreat next week again
we're going to focus on medicine buddha
practice
because of the virus and it's a very
powerful practice and
obviously we'll try to do it as much as
we can
with this attitude of love for every
person in the universe not just for this
planet this is a small
world there are billions of worlds like
this and
if we can have this greater focus i
don't know
it's like if you catch all the fish in
the ocean you can catch one fish that
you want you see what i mean
something like that i mean we don't want
to catch fish but
if you could catch all the fish in the
whole ocean
then probably the one you would really
like uh
maybe it's a jew what's it called juju
fish
you probably catch the one you want okay
uh so we'll see you in episode 15. we're
going to be doing
a review of all of the big ideas
of this course and it's good for you and
it's good for me and
we've been going through very carefully
you know bit by bit by bit
and if we can go back and review
everything in one
session then we can get an appreciation
for the flow
and it'll be easier to remember what
happened during this retreat
okay see you then